so we can start with a verse or a few a
verse and a the first one is the
popular uh from the a vers the bud gave
in the v uh patient endurance is the
highest austerity Nana is the highest say the
austerity Nana is the highest say the
Buddhas for one gone forth does not harm
another and one who troubles another is
not a
renunciate so the word
therefore um patience translated
patience is
kti and um then there's another
Su that talks about the five factors
with which a person person would not be
able to enter samama samadi so correct
composure and it says um here biku does
not have
TTI for sights sounds smells tastes and
touches uh endowed with these five
things uh because unable to achieve
right composure and then it says the
opposite when a biku has CTI for Sight
sounds smells tastes and touches then he
can achieve um red composure
so like basically we could see
that um obviously there's a there's a
general component of patience that
everyone could relate to like as it says
one who troubles another one who annoys
another out of impatience is
not um a real renunciate so that's like
the widest sense that everyone would be
able to relate to but then it says if
you don't have CTI for sense objects you
can't achieve somei so that's clearly
talking about something
deeper so what is what is
so what is what is
Cy to start off with
well as you said the meaning of the
words is like patience or
forbearance or maybe even endurance
County so what do you what are you
patient towards what do you end is the
question because anyone can practice
patience but
then as it says if it's if it's it's not
if it's not on the same level as niana
because that verse is talking about
nibana mhm um it's not like a
coincidence that it's mentioned next to
next to this it's not like he's talking
about worldly patience like I just wait
for stuff and then the next passage is
talking about Nana it's not a
um they're related basically the mention
of K there is not accidental no that's
actually a good point so the patience is
not like I'm just waiting for some
reward or for something that's going to
happen to me yeah rather um the question
arises you know how much control does
one have over the situation one finds
oneself in so in terms of sides and
sounds and smells you know if these
things if it is correctly seen that
these things arise on their
own and that one doesn't suffer on
account of the presence of those things
but on account of another
Factor then the true meaning of patience
stands out right
there but as long as someone thinks that
they suffer because of things in the
world I think the view that or the
entitlement that they can be otherwise
and should be otherwise then one can
become very impatient out of a desire to
change things because on things that if
one finds on in the perfect situation
one suffer but that's completely
regarding things the wrong way around
that's that's not where the origin of
the problem
is so uh how what would be the most
practical or the most the first way that
a person should should apply that
endurance or that
patience without which they wouldn't be
able to do it
properly Thea The Virtue
Thea The Virtue
yeah yeah so what is it that one needs
to be patient with in the context of the
correct s and why would lack of patience
make one either not keep the Sila at all so
one either not keep the Sila at all so
start breaking it or keep it wrongly
[Music] basically
so if if we see Sila as a kind of
boundaries which we delineate for our
engagement with the world
then uh patience in that respect will be
uh patience in that respect will be
keeping Within These boundaries staying
within the boundaries kind of generally
speaking and what what would you have to
be patient towards
like or rather where would there be
impatience when you're trying to stay
within those
boundaries all the all the pressures to
to act you know with with un wholesome
to act out of
pressure yeah so the patients would be
not in terms so this would be the
difference in terms of what you were
saying it's not like towards a future
reward that you're patient with if
anything it's like the real patience is
to something present something that's
present now not towards something you're
waiting for in the future so it would be
like you wouldn't be able to keep Sila
if you can't
endure the displeasure that arises now
on account of keeping these
precepts and like that's that's on a
basic level but then so a person can
still experience some sense of
discomfort taking on the the precepts
because they were not used to it but
they they can still um do them with an
attitude of non County like they can
still be externally following everything
basically keeping the rules very
strictly but then internally they're
still not
enduring so it's basically
um when if you can take on those
precepts for the purpose of not
experiencing the displeasure of um
things in the world like you can you can
use it as a form of hiding away from
things basically and that would that
would also be a form of non-un so it
would be like
um you're not really developing
yourself to to be able not to make these
choices instead you want to like not
even be not even have to consider
whether you you have to make these
choices you kind of want just the
choices to be automatically made by the
environment by the tradition by the by
the rules that you have decided
beforehand and not having to yourself be
responsible for saying yes or no yeah
there's an element of fear in that yeah
and that fear often results in
Conformity to something external
whereas um when the whereas the two
virtue as we said many times before is
more on the level of intention and not
on the Conformity to something external
this could also be like Conformity to
the past to a tradition to certain views
that you have bed for a long time that
doesn't necessarily mean that any of
that's there right or that one can be
impatient with conclusions on that level
yeah so as long as you
basically as long as your motivation for
keeping the virtue is not feeling the
responsibility for saying
no that personal responsibility then
you're doing it out of
non-un like it's it's certainly better
it is like a Improvement of kti compared
to someone who's not keeping them at all
so like it's still beneficial but in the
sense of like uh you know to get this
samadi right composure that is talking
about and Achieve Nana like you need to
go beyond just the the C of the obvious
level just okay I can I can be celibate
now yeah but why like are you are you
really um aware of that personal
responsibility there or kind you just
covered it up you just okay I decide to
do this now because that's what this
tradition does and then that's said you
don't revisit that decision again um you
don't you don't endure the discomfort of
of
uncertainty because through that
endurance is how you you would really
like make make the mind is passionate
towards those things through Cy
ironically through enduring things if
you if you don't endure this pleasure
then you're not really developing you're
kind of just
circumstantially adhering to
something yeah so to take on uh full
responsibility for finding oneself in
the world also brings pressure like on
the existential level and that one also
needs to endure in order to see
the origin of all that so to the extent
that one is finding excuses which is the
same as saying to the extent that allows
room for
inauthenticity there is an element of
nony there yeah so like that's I
there yeah so like that's I
mean I'm not sure if there's a better
word because patience kind of in in
English at least always implies like oh
you're waiting as we said before waiting
for something in the future but uh I
don't think the body word even has that
implication it's just
like um like something is there and
um like something is there and
you're at ease with its being there
basically you're you're not um trying to
go left and right from it the Buddha the
Buddha kind of defines it as as an
elephant he oh yeah he gave it a Sim of
an elephant that can like a battle
elephant that can cany the the blows of
Spears and the sounds of the enemy
drones so it's always something that you
have there now it's not like because
ironically as soon as you're thinking of
like give me a reward which is the
usually how what patience means it's
like you are discontent with what you
have now because you're looking for the
reward already yeah so um it's it's more
like uh endurance basically in mangala
as well there one stanza you know which
says uh Al in contact with the world
unshaken the
AR yeah there's that's that's another
thing so like again as we mentioned that
that verse is saying oh kti is the
highest austerity so and it puts it next
to niana so it's uh there's another Su
where where um the Buddha is talking
about the six senses and he says what is
um what is the arant what is how do you
define an arant and it says it's um the
pressure the he compared it with like
the ocean has a tide or has a current
the thing that's pushing the waves and
then he says the eye is is the current
for a person and then the one who can
endure that current is has gone beyond
so then that's how how it defines the
not in terms of like he doesn't
experience things anymore no so that kti
like it would be
basically connected with
um that's basically what freedom from
craving is like when you don't when you
have full County then craving becomes
redundant so like if you're fully
enduring if you're fully patient with
what you have now then why would you
need something
else so yeah so to the extent that one
wants things to be otherwise which
involves craving for or against things
there is non County yeah and that
wanting things to be otherwise shouldn't
just be understood as in a in a core
sense obviously you start like that like
you start restraining your actions that
are coly involved with wanting things to
be otherwise but even on a more subtle
level like meditation can be very often
rooted in nonan because um what well
let's let's get into that like how do
you why is it that this they saying that
without enduring sight sounds taste and
touches you wouldn't get right composure
meaning like when we say oh meditation
techniques and focusing methods and
wrong composure means this is why it's
because it's it's based on nonan so like
how does that practically happen that um
you could be trying to develop
somebody wrongly because
non well this this role of sensor
strength in the gradual training it's
quite a beginning of the whole process
isn't it begins with the virtue but then
sense restraint starts so this is quite
a fundamental kind of
uh uh beginning of the training of the
Mind composing mind yeah but he is
asking with what intention does one take
up even the restraint because you see
somebody could be restrained yeah but
still then start practicing methods and
techniques and certainly not with
intention to get rid of things but just
more like a meeting things rather not
not trying to get rid of yeah but you
see somebody could focus on an object in
front of them candle flame color clay
disc picture of the Buddha say something
something like that but why why would he
no no want to do it yeah well that's
exactly the point so somebody might
think oh I I need a meditation object in
the sense that popularly meditation is
thought like you know be with your
object something like that and then
might not somebody might not recognize
that there is an element of resistance
in that whole setup like I to focus on
one thing and to see a development in
that direction that by definition
implies that you leave a whole bunch of
other things out so there's already a
conflict there and I need to stay with
this and not with everything else and
why why is it that everything else has
to be shut out because well precisely
because one is incapable of enjoying
this totally IR experience and as long
as that's the case how is one even going
to see based on what that is the
totality of this pres experience well
how how would you like how would you
free yourself when you're because as the
Buddha said
somei uh knowledge and vision depends on
Sam so if your samadi is based on this
like separate world yeah that you go
into or this one little corner any any
knowledge that you get rise to whether
it's valid or not it's going to be about
this tiny Corner yeah it's not going to
be about the rest yeah so and so but
then somebody might say no no I figure
out the principle there and then I apply
it to the rest of my experience but
that's not how it works it's that would
be like a logical conclusion like I
extract the the principle from this but
that's not how the Buddhist talked about
it he said it's direct seeing yeah so
the usual approach would be basically
wanting to replace something yeah yeah
yeah so that would be wrong attitude
basically because it's rooted in non
like instead of basically instead of
cultivating or developing yourself so
that you can endure the feeling without
craving you just create another feeling
that you can endure because it's
Pleasant but not seeing that the right pleasure
but not seeing that the right pleasure
that the Buddha is talking about depends
on when things don't go the way you want
and you basically are a quanus towards
having things that you don't want to
have there basically so ironically that
pleasure that's dependent on non count
it's it's still dependent on acquisition
still dependent on like having it the
way you want basically because you
couldn't just
you couldn't just be equanimous you
couldn't just be dispassionate towards
this you had to move to something else
and then even if you come back to the
thing that you had
before uh it doesn't feel the same
anymore so it's it's uh so you can say
that on the level of sense restraint
that's the first place where things may
go not your way basically yeah and
that's why
yes and that's exactly why if a person
skips that sensor straint and then goes
right into the meditation like they
haven't developed this basic they
haven't understood what meditation is
exctly That's So then when they then
when they go into um like doing this
meditation is going to be something
entirely different whereas it would be closer
different whereas it would be closer
like meditation properly speaking we'll
be closer to learning how to practice
sensorship because
that's already like you have to put up
with these things you you don't like you
can reduce your environment um your
environmental exposure and you have to
um to a great degree but inevitably
things will start coming up like there's
no way that you can uh hide yourself
away from Pleasure and Pain uh
ultimately so um when that starts to
happen you need to then find out how to
not be moved by those things and that
happens through endurance so then that's
already like if you if you want to
Define meditation as cultivation of the
Mind cultivation of equanimity that's
where it starts sensor strength yeah and
also one wants to consider like do you
have control over the physical body that you
control over the physical body that you
are bound up with like if you get sick
right old old age when you when you
realize that you're not in a position to
prevent these things from happening um
then you would better prepare yourself
because basically the whole situation
going downhill on that level at that
point when those things start to come up
um that's
where like the the methods that you
developed on the basis of
nonan at at a certain point they would
they would not apply anymore because
because uh now that's the kind of
displeasure that's the kind of dis
pleasure that you can't run away from
like you can kind of hide from sight
sound smells taste touches that kind of
come from the world but when the
pleasure is coming from your senses like
when it's uh sickness aging death well
the only thing you can do basically is
like put yourself to sleep or something
but then like you die a Mindless death
and that's not that's not a it's it's
not a Improvement in the end compared to
somebody else who who is not meditating
M so or bit on smoth as well like you
know you can wake up in the morning be
in a in a pretty F mood and it's not
that you can just start doing things in
order to to change that yeah well like
that's a that's why it's a it's such a
kind of um danger because it can work to
some extent like if if if people invest
a lot of effort into it like into
techniques and stuff it can work and it
can feel like oh generally I'm in a good
mood all the time where I can get rid of
it very quickly but the point is you
being able to do that depends on many
conditions and many circumstances that
are going well for you like if you
weren't healthy probably you wouldn't
you wouldn't be able to do that um or
you wouldn't have been able to develop
that you wouldn't have been able to get
there and uh like it doesn't matter uh
how much a person feels like they can
endure or sorry that they can escape
basically in that wrong way through
non-endurance through focusing or
through U man fabricating some kind of
pleasure um there's always going to be
something that's beyond your comfort
zone yeah even if you haven't
experienced it there has to be something
that has to shatter that um that facade
that you developed and
that's because otherwise you are
basically assuming that you are in full
control of the whole world yeah it's a
way of assuming that you can control
your feelings yeah and and that's that's
that's uh that's impossible so then um
at the moment of death most
importantly that's why endurance is the
highest like that's what endurance is
the death L basically because at the
moment of death that's where you genely
like when the Buddha wanted to describe
any kind of severe pain he said death or
death like suffering in the Su is always
he it wasn't because like oh the the
bodily pain that you kind of bodily
Sensations that you
experience um it's it's that sense of
like losing control totally and um
that's where the point where uh no
matter how much focusing you have
practiced no matter how much Pleasant
moods you've been able to kind of
fabricate at the very latest that's the
point where it won't work because that's
where like your your mind is not
listening to you at all anymore
basically so that's where you would have
to just that pure endurance that pure
non-resistance to discomfort that's when
when it would be tested before that
point anything might go your way you
might even you know if if if you're
lucky enough that um you don't reach old
age or the sicknesses that you experienc
during your old age are not that severe
then maybe you can get away still with
the same sort of avoid voidance but at
the very latest at the moment of death
that's where nobody can escape basically
unless somebody who has developed right endurance so
endurance so
then when someone does see let's say
that feelings are not self that mood is
not self basically a noble disciple well
is is it that like how would can we so
if you right so so what would be the
meaning of patience from the point of
view of having already The View right
yeah so I would I would instead before
we get to that one it would be a good
question to say as well how does
patience lead you to see things because
because then um that's a that's a that's
an important connection because then um
the the sense of like appropriation of
feeling happens not through I mean
usually people have the idea that oh I
just think or choose to think that
things are mine it's some sort of idea
that's floating in my mind and if I just
change that idea well things are not
mine anymore but the appropriation
happens exactly through the lack of CI
it's through not being able to endure
things that's like the basis for any
sort of uh notion of mind that you could
have because as soon as you need it to
be otherwise you will be assuming that
you can make it otherwise and that's the
Assumption of ownership basically that's
so it's just the Assumption or the
appropriation is there to meet the need
that's created by your lack of
Cy so that's why if a person develops
CTI which is through virtue sense
restraints basically the gradual
training um even all the way to samadi
which is um evidently the same principle
then that's removing the obstacles for
them to understand not self because like
at that point the Assumption of self
ceases to have a purpose like why would
you would you assume why would you need
this to be otherwise yes if you have
country yes so the Assumption of self of
being someone is is being fueled is
being maintained by acting out of that
pressure that involves you and
entitlement of one things to be otherz
uh it's it's Fu so
the the nony is fueled by not acting out
but then like no no the county is fueled
by not acting out sorry yeah the non
county is fueled by acting out that's it
yeah and so um the the Assumption itself
is fed by the tendency to want to act
down basically that's it yeah so like
even if you're not acting out let's say
temporarily you might still the like the
tend that has been built is still there so
that has been built is still there so
it's like it's that kind of
um energy if you want to use that word
like that's that's there even if it's
not manifesting but you still have that
kind of tendency to want to manipulate
your feelings yeah that's not uprooted
yeah and so the um and that's another
thing actually the Buddha when when he
talked about not self the very second
discourse he gave the
anak he was not talking in terms of like
Notions and views of this is mine or
this is not mine he was talking about um
can you have
form uh the fact that that you cannot
say may my form be like this may my form
not be like this that's why form is not
self so he was talking about it always
in the sense of that lack of control
never in the sense of like this doesn't
exist or it's an illusion or or it's
it's it's yeah it's not a metaphysical
statement yeah yeah exactly so it's it's
based on this like based on
kti you have the having developed kti
let's say you have The
Bravery to recognize that you can't
control these things for as long as you
don't have Cy like impulsively
necessarily you will be feeling that you
have to be able to control it and that's
why like a person who hasn't developed
virtue who hasn't developed sensory
strength who hasn't developed Cy if they
got to see like some glimpse of what
anata is they would not feel happy about
it they would feel horrified because
it's like I have this need to control
things and now I'm recognizing that I
can't even even do it even if I want to
MH so that's why um like niana if K has
not been developed beforehand is
unpleasant because it's like recognition
of non-ownership while you still depend
depend on ownership because you need to
you're not able to endure it basically
yeah so all of The Graduate training all
of this kind of previous development
that has to happen for a person to
understand dama just basically improving
the country on various levels of refinement
country on various levels of refinement
like the Buddha was asked once like what
is the aim of
Aesthetics what is their
Quest and then it goes on like what is their
and then it goes on like what is their
support what are they intend on and
what's the final goal and then the
Buddha says the Buddha said the aim of
Aesthetics is patience County and
gentleness and then their Quest is for
Wisdom their support is virtue their
intent on
nothingness and their final goals
[Music] Nana so it starts out by saying what is
Nana so it starts out by saying what is
what is the aim of nence of Aesthetics
is is Cy right for parents or um
enduring things rightly and also a sense
of gentleness because you see in one's
relationship to other people as well if
somebody is in impatient can be real
pain in the neck whereas when somebody
is capable of of enduring your bad mood
or something clumsy they're harmless as
well and they have a sense of
friendliness and um and and and sympathy
then this is how by looking after others
one also takes care of oneself yeah so
that too begins with with a sense of of
patience this is perhaps a bit more on
the on the worldly plane still but it
seems to me that that goes all the way
yeah and like again we have to emphasize
patient is not in the sense of like oh
I'm waiting for this person to change
because that's again you're resisting
the is no you don't care whether they
change or not you're just enduring that
discomfort so even if they stay like
that for the rest of the life you're not
suffering that's when you have patient
tempting basically that kind of ties
into what I wanted to ask about which
was um kind of the idea of
not trying to
endure the basically your own
the basically your own
craving um you were talking about that
to me the other day um what are kind
kind
of yeah could we just talk about that
for a minute um yeah so uh actually we
we were kind of leading to that with the
thing about seeing not self and seeing
uh how kti is the basis for that so you
would be able to
basically all these insights that the
Buddha talks about like what is actually
craving for example unless you're able
to endure things you will never find out
what craving is because like your
automatic reaction is to get rid of the
displeasure like anything that's even in
the name of meditation as we were saying
before like just get rid of this object
that displeases me and replace it with
the one that's Pleasant so then you
would just be maintaining your
assumption that craving is the same as
displeasure because that's what a
contusion of leaves like not not
consciously of course but that's like
the the misconceiving that's present
it's like not being able to see that
this pleasure is one thing and craving
is basically lay it on top of it
gratuitously like it doesn't have to be
there so you can experience any amount
of
displeasure and craving is kind of not
supposed to be there it does it
shouldn't be there so through enduring
things anything basically like not just
again not just uh
because I wanted to mention that as well
like usually okay people can take
endurance in the sense of of the
practice but then they might do it
overly externally like oh I'm going to
endure hunger um cold heat which the
Buddha said you should do but
then people don't realize it's not about
these bodily
Sensations that I need to endure it's
the discomfort the mental kind of
emotional um unsafety or or uh emotional
sort of um angst that comes up to some
degree like feeling exposed basically
that's what you have to endure so like
as soon as your practice of enduring the
elements for example
becomes uh enjoyable becomes Pleasant
like it probably was for some Aesthetics
back in the day like they generally get
get a kick out of out of um torturing
themselves then you're not enduring even
if you're putting up with the sharpest
bodily pain it's not endurance anymore
because it's not the feeling has changed
like feeling is not the same as
sensation it's two completely different
things so uh it's always about recognizing that
so uh it's always about recognizing that
you have to endure the feeling any
feeling that comes uh from any direction
you have to learn to basically endure it
without falling into um trying to make
it otherwise so that you can then endure
it like trying to make myself not feel
the cold or or not feel this pleasure in
account of the cold so that I can endure
the cold that's not the not really I mean
cold that's not the not really I mean
it's it's a kind of development on a on
a worldly sense you could say uh but
it's not a development of the mind which
is always in regard to
feeling so all of this feeds into what
we discussed earlier in the context of
the middle way as well that that is
basically like the right County that
leads to the Nana has to be that yeah I
think we mentioned that before that um
any practice that you're doing like
whether is virtue sensor strange or even
like you know watching your intentions
and and uh purifying your mind from un
wholesome states is it would all be
determined as right or wrong based on
whether you have
kti if your any of those practices can
become wrong if kti is lost like you can
be doing the same virtue externally the
same sensor strange you can be trying to
pufy your mind from thoughts of
sensuality but if you're doing it
without kti basically trying to get rid
of the feeling that's there then it's
not really the middle way anymore that's
when you get into self modification
yeah so there's the Su which talks about
the handle of an ax right Noble disciple
practicing the noble a path he is just
reflecting on his Noble Right View and
think we have discussed before but he's
not actually concerned on a daily basis
like oh this is how much the handle of
this chicken the hand in the X yeah so
about the simil so he so he's not
concerned that all the handle of this x
has been worn away this much or that
much at some point he just
noticed this whole hand is gone
basically that's a that's a good one to
bring up because so uh I mean obviously
that's what is in the context of no
disciple but it applies to everyone like
for as long as um it says the person is
not focused on oh I want this result
it's focused on wearing the a handle
down so um because why because it's not
like it's not saying like um how do you
put it like go it's harmful or it's or it's
it like go it's harmful or it's or it's
uh pointless if you're expecting a
result it's like literally on account of
this you're not actually developing
because you're not enduring right there
and there like you want the reward out
of this meaning you're you're you have a
problem with this feeling that's now you
have a problem with well the pain of not
being enlightened for example so you'll
be closer closer to actually developing
your mind by enduring the the pain of
wanting to be en lightened than by just
assuming that desire or hope as fine and
then like craving basically for that and
then acting out of that one way or
another yeah so so like enduring
ignorance enduring the recognition that
you still are ignorant basically that
your mind still has the fits is closer
to abing of the fets than just allowing
yourself to to try to get rid of them in
any way you you feel is appropriate so
um because again that would be um
basically like unless you understand
rightly and you have the right
view um for you the idea of what the
fets are is always mixed with what
feeling is so like a person would be
trying to get rid of the fets but more
often than not they will be just trying
to get rid of feelings because they
don't see that separation that
separation between what is a pleasant
feeling and what is sensuality what is
unpleasant feeling and what is aversion
that can only be recognized with the
Right View that's where the the that's
where um well that's where why it says
ma9 that only no deciple understands
wholesome is wholesome and UNH wholesome
is UN wholesome because that's when you
can separate okay so this is the actual
part that is in my control which is the
defilement and this is the part that
arises on itself own um so that's also
like seeing the sign of the Mind
recognizing the extent to which things
are just
given which is feelings and the extent
to which you're basically either
enduring them or not which is wholesome
or un
wholesome yeah and this notion of not
being fully completely enlightened yet
and the craving involved in that that
that is paired with ill will like that
can be a sense of aggression or ill will
in one's attitude towards oneself like
why why do I not have that but as you
just said like by um by enduring that or
having patience on on the right level
even in relation to that that is how how
one actually can give up that ill will
which is which is precisely the let's
say gentleness or meekness which is
often paired with the country so that's
why there's like there's no
justification ever to say this feeling I
don't need to endure these others one
the these other ones I do because that's
where that's where the Buddha says oh um
any feeling course like course or fine
and fears bear uh past or present or
future all feelings should be seen in
the same way so like you shouldn't be
making exceptions for okay the feeling
of um like for example the the feeling I
get when I have a sensual thought it's
an unpleasant feeling and I assume that
because the Buddha says you have to get
rid of central thoughts I am justified
of getting rid of this feeling you have
to get rid of the sensual thought not
get rid of the feeling so that's why
like a person needs to to recognize that
there is a distinction there to be Rec
to be to be seen like um the the
displeasure of any un wholesome state
that you might be experiencing is not
the same as the UN wholesome State
itself so if you just assume and allow
yourself to get rid of it uh like on
impulse basically you'll basically just
be throwing the baby out with the bath
water as the say goh so a person needs
to learn like how to endure things
without giving into them at the same
time because for most people like say oh
no I don't have to get rid of it I just
have to endure it then that means oh I
stay with the sentral thought now but
I'm kind of delighting in it still so
it's still kind of being um too loose
and too careless mhm so it's like always
finding that right balance how do I not
welcome things how how do I remain
dispassionate towards things but without
trying to get rid of them
and dispassion as well um Can often be
thought of as like oh I need to be kind
of uh not feeling things anymore so as
to be dispassionate like I I just
basically confused with like apathy yeah
so the because the dispassion is
precisely in relation to feeling yeah
exactly so it's not like dispassion is
not lack of feeling this passion is like
not needing to act out no matter what
feeling is there yeah
because apathy is just like again it's
like no stimulus therefore no
response but that's not that's that's
not not training yeah that's
overshooting the mark yeah yeah like if
if if you say I won
because there's no threat
anymore or or I'm safe because there's
no threat anymore well that's a
circumstantial safety you have to be
safe when there is a threat
essentially and every feeling basically
is a threat yeah